"Why Do Milk Drinkers Live
Shorter Lives on Average?"
In my video
on milk and bones,
I discussed
this set of studies,
following a hundred thousand
people for up to two decades,
finding a 60% higher risk
of hip fracture
among women who drank
a lot of milk.
The researchers suggested it
might be due to the galactose,
which is a breakdown product
of the milk sugar lactose,
based on the fact that people
with high levels in their blood,
because they were born with an
inability to detoxify the stuff,
can end up
with weakened bones.
But that's not all
galactose can do.
Galactose is what scientists use
to cause accelerated aging
in lab animals,
since it's so successful
at mimicking aging
by inducing degenerative changes
in the brain,
heart, lungs, liver,
kidney, etc.
"Life-shortened animals
showed neurodegeneration,
mental retardation,
and cognitive dysfunction,
diminished immune responses
and a reduction
of reproductive ability."
And it doesn't take much,
just the human equivalent
of one to two glasses worth
of milk a day.
However, humans aren't rodents.
For example, we've known
for nearly a century
that you can cause cataracts
in rats
by feeding them lots
of lactose or galactose,
but the epidemiological data
is mixed
as to whether dairy
is doing the same in people.
The Swedish studies didn't
just look at bone, though,
but milk and mortality.
More milk was associated
with more death.
In women,
three glasses of milk a day
was associated with nearly twice
the risk of dying prematurely.
The medical journal editorial
accompanying the study
emphasized that,
given the rise
in milk consumption
around the world,
the "role of milk in mortality
needs to be established
definitively now."
With the then-largest-ever study
on milk intake and mortality
suggesting such adverse effects,
Harvard researchers stepped in
with three of their cohorts
to form a study twice as big
to see if the earlier findings
were just a fluke.
Following more than
200,000 men and women
for up to three decades,
they confirmed the bad news.
Those who consumed more dairy
lived significantly shorter
lives.
Every half serving more
of regular milk a day
was associated with
9% increased risk of dying
from cardiovascular disease,
11% increased risk
of dying from cancer,
and an 11% increased risk
of dying
from all causes put together.
This is all the more remarkable
since milk drinking
is typically associated
with healthier habits,
like more exercise
and less smoking and drinking,
though they did try to control
for all these factors.
Of course it does matter
what you eat instead.
This Harvard analysis published
in the New England Journal
of Medicine,
found that swapping dairy
for meat,
red meat, poultry, or fish,
would not be expected
to do your body any favors,
and you would be expected
to live longer eating dairy
than eggs or processed meat.
It's only when you swap dairy
for plant-based sources
of protein
did they find a significant drop
in mortality risk.
When all of the milk
and mortality studies
are put together,
it appears
the excess mortality risk
is limited to regular as opposed
to low-fat, like skim milk.
This suggests it may be more
of a saturated fat issue,
though that doesn't explain why
soured, or fermented milk
appears to have
the opposite impact.
So maybe it's both the butterfat
and the galactose.
A randomized crossover study
of low-fat dairy,
fermented dairy,
and unfermented dairy
found that study subjects
had significantly higher
IL-6 inflammation levels
during unfermented
regular dairy weeks
compared to when they were
switched to either
the fermented
or low-fat dairy products.
The fermentation process can
eliminate some of the galactose.
As we age, our ability
to detoxify galactose
declines by as much as 40%,
which would make it
even more important
to avoid dairy later in life
if indeed galactose
is the culprit.
But if galactose
does its dirty work
through oxidation
and inflammation,
might increased fruit
and vegetable intake
help mediate some of the harm?
In animals,
galactose-induced aging
can be slowed by fruit
and vegetable consumption.
For example,
feeding rats blueberries
can decrease the brain damage
induced by the milk sugar.
Might it be able to help
with the higher levels
of oxidative stress
and inflammation found
among human milk drinkers?
Unfortunately, women drinking
three or more glasses of milk
a day had more than twice
the risk of hip fractures
compared to women drinking
less than a glass a day
regardless of whether
they were eating more, or less,
fruits and vegetables.
But, those high milk consumers
consuming five or more servings
of fruits and vegetables a day
did reduce their chance
of dying prematurely
to just 60% greater
than those drinking less milk,
so antioxidant rich foods
may be able to modify
the elevated death rate
associated with
high milk consumption.
Highly influential
advocacy organizations,
such as the US National
Osteoporosis Foundation
or the Europe-based
International
Osteoporosis Foundation,
continue to push dairy, drugs,
and calcium supplements,
despite the countervailing
evidence that I've reviewed.
Why do they keep pushing dairy,
drugs, and supplements?
Perhaps because their
objectivity is compromised
by the influence
of their commercial sponsors
that include companies
that market, you guessed it,
dairy, drugs,
and supplements.
Most recent reviews
on dairy and osteoporosis
in the English-language
medical literature
were found to be written
by those with ties
to the dairy industry.
The primary justification
for inclusion of dairy
in federal nutrition
recommendations
is based on
purported bone benefits
that are not supported
by the available evidence.
What if dietary guidelines
were fashioned
without commercial influence?
In 2019, Canada decided
to exclude industry reports
and stick to the science
in the formation
of their new dietary guidelines.
What a concept.
Major changes
include the new emphasis
on plant-based food intake,
limiting junk,
and...the removal
of the dairy food group.